2 0 0 1  太 空 漫 游
（人类的诞生）
好了 先生 请到主楼层
Here you are, sir. Main level, please.
好吧 待会儿见
Right. See you on the way back.
- 再见 - 再见
- Bye. - Bye.
- 早安 先生  - 早安
- Good morning, sir. - Morning.
好久不见
We haven't seen you for a long time.
很高兴能再见到你
Nice to see you again.
- 一路还顺利吗   - 非常顺利 谢谢
- Did you have a pleasant flight? - Very nice.
我跟太空站安全部米勒先生约好了
Mr. Miller of Station Security is supposed to meet me.
- 需要我帮你联络他吗   - 可以吗 他来了
- May I call him for you? - Would you? Here he is.
- 你好 弗洛伊德博士 - 你好 米勒
- Hello, Dr. Floyd. - Hello, Miller.
- 抱歉我迟到了  - 没关系
- Sorry I'm late. - That's all right.
很高兴你回来了
It's nice to have you back.
- 一路顺风吗   - 非常顺利
- Did you have a good flight? - Very nice.
我们可以进去了吗
Shall we go through?
请走17号通道
Would you please use number 17?
谢谢你 特纳小姐
Thank you, Ms. Turner.
- 这边请  - 谢谢
- This way. - Thank you.
（英文 荷兰文 俄文 法文 意大利文 日文）
欢迎使用语音辨识系统
Welcome to Voiceprint Identification.
红灯亮起时
When you see the red light go on,
请依照下列指令顺序操作
please state in the following order:
你的目的地
Your destination,
国籍跟全名
your nationality and your full name.
先说姓 再说名字跟缩写
Surname first, Christian name, and initial.
月球 美国人
Moon. American.
弗洛伊德 海伍德·R
Floyd, Heywood R.
谢谢 你通过语音辨识了
Thank you. You are cleared through Voiceprint Identification.
谢谢
Thank you.
我有空吃早餐吗
Have I got time for breakfast?
我们可以安排
I think we can manage that.
我有多少时间
How long have I got?
你的太空船一小时十分钟后出发
Your flight leaves in an hour and 10 minutes.
我帮你在地照室留了个位置
I've reserved a table for you in the Earthlight Room.
你已经七 八个月没过来了吧
It's been seven or eight months since you were here, hasn't it?
让我想想 对 大约八个月
Let's see. Yeah, about eight months.
你应该看到新部门的成果了吧
I suppose you saw the work on the new section?
- 结果很不错吧   - 的确很不错
- Coming along great, huh? - Yeah, it's fine.
等一下
Oh, wait.
我得打几通电话 我们到餐厅碰面
I've got to make a couple calls. I'll meet you in the restaurant.
（准备通话）
- 爸  - 你好
- Dad? - Hello.
小鬼 你在做什么
Hi, squirt. What are you doing?
我在玩
Playing.
妈妈在哪里
Where's Mummy?
她去买东西
Gone to shopping.
谁在照顾你
Who's taking care of you?
蕾切尔
Rachel.
我能跟蕾切尔说话吗
May I speak to Rachel, please?
她去上厕所了
She's gone to the bathroom.
明天你会来参加我的派对吗
Are you coming to my party tomorrow?
抱歉 甜心 我没办法去
I'm sorry, sweetheart, but I can't.
为什么
Why not?
爸爸在旅行
Well, you know, Daddy's traveling.
真的很抱歉 我不能去
Very sorry about it, but I just can't.
但我要送你很棒的礼物
I'm going to send you a very nice present, though.
好吧
All right.
你有特别想要的东西吗
Anything special that you want?
有啊
Yes.
是什么
What?
电话
A telephone.
我们已经有很多电话了
We've got lots of telephones already.
你不能想些别的生日礼物吗
Can't you think of anything else for your birthday?
非常特别的东西
Something special?
- 有了  - 什么
- Yes. - What?
一只灌丛婴猴
A bush baby.
灌丛婴猴 我会想办法的
A bush baby? We'll have to see about that.
我要你帮我转告妈妈一件事 你能记住吗
I want you to tell Mummy something for me. Will you remember?
告诉妈妈我打过电话 好吗
Tell Mummy that I telephoned. Okay?
明天我会再打电话
And that I'll try to telephone again tomorrow.
你能告诉她吗
Now, will you tell her that?
可以
Yes.
好吧 甜心 祝你明天生日快乐
Okay, sweetheart. Have a nice birthday tomorrow.
好的
All right.
还要祝你明天生日派对玩得开心
And have a nice birthday party tomorrow too, huh?
好吧
All right.
保重 当个乖女孩 好吗
Take care and be a good girl, won't you?
好的 再见
All right. Bye-bye.
再见 生日快乐
Bye-bye. Happy birthday.
（收费1元7角 谢谢）
艾琳娜
Elena,
- 真高兴能再见到你  - 海伍德 这真是天大的惊喜
- nice to see you again. - Heywood, what a surprise.
- 你的气色好极了  - 你也是
- You're looking wonderful. - You're looking well too.
他是我的朋友海伍德·弗洛伊德博士
This is my friend, Dr. Heywood Floyd.
- 这位是凯琳娜博士  - 你好吗
- I'd like you to meet Dr. Kalinan. - How do you do?
- 史崔泰妮娃博士  - 你好吗
- Dr. Stretyneva. - How do you do?
这位是安德烈·斯米斯洛夫博士
And this is Dr. Andrei Smyslov.
你好吗 我常听说你的丰功伟业
How do you do? I've heard a lot about you.
请坐
Do sit down.
- 我们…  - 不 请吧
- Well, we...  - No, no, please.
谢谢
Thank you.
- 你要喝点什么吗 博士   - 不用了 谢谢
- Would you like a drink? - No, thank you.
我还没有吃早餐
I haven't had breakfast yet.
跟人约好要在餐厅碰面
Someone's meeting me in the restaurant.
我坐一下就离开
I'll just sit with you a moment. Then I'll be off.
你确定
Are you quite sure?
我很确定 谢谢
Quite sure, thank you.
葛雷格还好吧
Well, how's Gregor?
他很好
He's fine.
他在波罗的海做深海研究
He's been doing underwater research in the Baltic...
我担心未来我们无法常常见面
so I'm afraid we don't see very much of each other these days.
- 看到他时帮我跟他问好  - 没问题
- When you see him, give him my regards. - Yes, of course.
你们要去哪里 往上或往下
Well, where are you all off to? Up or down?
我们要回家
We're going home.
我们在查林可号上待了三个月调整新天线@
We've spent three months calibrating the new antenna at Tchalinko.
你呢
What about you?
我要去卡拉维斯号
I'm on my way to Clavius.
是吗
Oh, are you?
弗洛伊德博士 我希望你不会认为我太多事
Dr. Floyd, I hope you don't think I'm being too inquisitive...
或许你可以解开谜团
but perhaps you can clear up the big mystery
说明那里到底发生了什么事
about what is going on there.
恐怕我不了解你的意思
I'm afraid I don't know what you mean.
过去两个星期以来
For the past two weeks...
卡拉维斯号上发生了怪事
some extremely odd things have been happening at Clavius.
- 真的吗   - 对
- Oh, really? - Yes, yes.
譬如打电话
For one thing,
到基地 只能听到电话录音
when you phone the base, all you get is a recording...
重覆说着电话线路暂时故障
which repeats that the phone lines are temporarily out of order.
或许他们的设备有问题
Probably having some trouble with their equipment.
对
Yes.
一开始我们是那么想的
That's what we thought at first,
但十天以来都是如此
but it's been going on now for 10 days.
你们十天来无法联络上任何人
You haven't been able to contact anyone for 10 days?
没错
That's right.
我懂了
Oh, I see.
还有一件事
There's another thing.
两天前一辆火箭巴士
Two days ago, one of our rocket buses...
被拒绝做紧急降落
was denied permission for an emergency landing.
那真的很奇怪
That does sound odd.
恐怕这件事会喧扰一阵
I'm afraid there's going to be a bit of a row about it.
拒绝降落违反 I AS协定
Denying the men permission to land violates the IAS Convention.
没错 机组人员都安全回来了吧
Yes, of course. Did the crew get back all right?
还好他们都很平安
Fortunately, they did.
真的是太好了
Well, I'm glad about that.
弗洛伊德博士
恕我继续追问下去 你似乎不太想谈
At the risk of pressing you on a point you seem reticent to discuss...
我能直接问你一件事吗
may I ask you a straightforward question?
没问题
Well, certainly.
老实说我们收到一些可靠的情报
Frankly, we have had some very reliable intelligence reports that...
卡拉维斯号上爆发严重传染病
quite a serious epidemic has broken out at Clavius.
很明显地病因不明
Something, apparently, of an unknown origin.
那是真的吗
Is this, in fact, what has happened?
抱歉 斯米斯洛夫博士
I'm sorry, Dr. Smyslov, but...
我真的不能谈论此事
I'm really not at liberty to discuss this.
我了解
I understand.
但这个传染病很容易就会蔓延到我们的基地
But this epidemic could easily spread to our base.
我们应该知道真相
We should be given all the facts.
我知道
Yes, I know.
我说过我不能谈论此事
As I said, I'm not at liberty to discuss it.
你确定真的不要喝点东西
Won't you change your mind about that drink?
对 我真的该走了
No, I'm positive. I really must be going.
希望你跟你太太能参加六月的IAC大会
I hope you and your wife come to the IAC Conference.
我们希望有空参加
I hope we can make it.
如果你们真的要来 记得带你们的宝贝女儿来
If you do, bring that darling little daughter with you.
那得看学校会不会放假
That'll depend on school vacations and all that sort of thing.
有机会的话我们会带她去的
If we can, we will.
如果你到了美国 一定要来拜访我们
You've got an invitation if you ever get to the States.
葛雷格和我很期待跟你们见面
Gregor and I will look forward to seeing you.
再见 艾琳娜
Goodbye, Elena.
很高兴能认识你们 斯米斯洛夫博士
It's been a pleasure meeting you all. Dr. Smyslov.
不论你来这里是为了什么
Whatever the reasons for your visit,
祝你好运
the very best of luck to you.
谢谢
Thank you.
再见 两位
Ladies.
（无重力厕所）
（使用前请详阅说明）
不好意思 哈佛森博士
Excuse me, Dr. Halvorsen.
我的工作结束了  谢谢各位
I'm through now. Thank you very much, gentlemen.
别客气
You're welcome.
好吧
Well...
我知道大家都想与我一起…
I know you will all want to join with me...
欢迎我们的好朋友及同事
in welcoming our distinguished friend and colleague...
来自全国太空航行议会的海伍德·弗洛伊德博士
from the National Council of Astronautics, Dr. Heywood Floyd.
今天弗洛伊德博士特地来…
Dr. Floyd has come up specially...
跟我们一起去卡拉维斯号
to Clavius to be with us today.
做简报前他想跟大家说说话
Before the briefing, he'd like to have a few words with you.
弗洛伊德博士
Dr. Floyd?
谢谢你 哈佛森博士
Thank you, Dr. Halvorsen.
大家好 很高兴能再跟大家见面
Hi, everybody. Nice to be back with you.
首先霍威尔博士要我带话
First, I bring a personal message from Dr. Howell...
他请我代表他对你们所做的牺牲
who has asked me to convey his deep appreciation...
致上深深的感谢
for the many sacrifices you've had to make.
当然他要恭喜你们的发现
And, of course, his congratulations on your discovery...
这应该是科学史上最伟大的成就
which may prove to be among the most significant in the history of science.
好了
Now...
我知道大家各有不同意见
I know there have been some conflicting views...
关于这件事的安全等级
regarding the need for complete security in this matter.
最重要的是你们反对编造故事
More specifically, your opposition to the cover story...
让大家以为基地爆发传染病
created to give the impression of an epidemic at the base.
我了解除了原则问题之外
I understand that beyond it being a matter of principle...
许多人都非常担忧
many of you are troubled by the concern and anxiety...
传染病的故事会影响到地球上的亲友
this story of an epidemic might cause to your relatives and friends on Earth.
我完全了解你们的负面看法
I completely sympathize with your negative views.
我自己也觉得这个说词很丢脸
I find this cover story personally embarrassing, myself.
但我同意这件事需要完全保密
However, I accept the need for absolute secrecy in this.
希望你们也有同感
And I hope you will too.
我相信大家都知道
I'm sure you're all aware of the grave potential...
这件事可能会
for cultural shock and social disorientation...
造成文化及社会上相当大的冲击
contained in this situation...
如果消息太早曝光
if the facts were prematurely made public...
而没有做适当的准备及处理的话
without adequate preparation and conditioning.
总之
Anyway...
这是议会的看法
this is the view of the Council.
我来这里是要针对这件事
The purpose of my visit is to gather additional facts and opinions...
收集真相及意见
on the situation...
跟议会提出报告
and to prepare a report to the Council...
建议时机与方法
recommending when and how the...
公布这个消息
news should eventually be announced.
如果你们愿意提供我想法跟意见
If any of you would like to give me your views and opinions...
私下讲也没有关系
in private, if you like,
我很乐意将它们纳入报告中
I will be happy to include them in my report.
大概就这样
Well, I think that's about it.
有问题吗
Any questions?
弗洛伊德博士
Dr. Floyd,
你知道这个谎言…
have you any idea how much longer...
还得维持多久吗
this cover story will have to be maintained?
我不知道 比尔
I don't know, Bill.
我想时间长短得由议会决定
I suppose for as long as deemed necessary by the Council.
我们得有时间做完整研究
There must be adequate time for a full study...
再考虑公布消息
before any thought can be given to making a public announcement.
有些人应该知道议会要求…
As some of you know, the Council has requested...
知道这件事的人
that security oaths be obtained in writing...
签下书面保密合约
from everyone who has knowledge of this event.
还有问题吗
Were there any more questions?
我相信我们会配合弗洛伊德博士
I'm sure we want to cooperate with Dr. Floyd...
而且是尽全力
as fully as possible...
如果没有问题了and as there are no more questions,
接下来我们得做简报
we ought to get on with the briefing.
- 谢谢你 弗洛伊德博士  - 谢谢
- Thank you, Dr. Floyd. - Thank you.
有人饿了吗
Anybody hungry?
- 太棒了  - 好吧
- 要吃什么   - 什么都有
- What've we got? - You name it.
- 这是鸡肉吗   - 类似啦
- Is this chicken? - Something like that.
反正味道都一样
Tastes the same, anyway.
有火腿吗
Got any ham?
火腿…
Ham, ham, ham....
有了 找到了
There, that's it.
看起来很不错
Look pretty good.
他们是越来越厉害了
They're getting better at it all the time.
你的演说非常精彩 海伍德
That was an excellent speech.
一点都没错
It certainly was.
我相信它大大地提振了士气
I'm sure it beefed up morale a lot.
谢谢你 雷夫
Thanks, Ralph.
对了 你们都表现得很好
By the way, you've both done a wonderful job.
我很佩服你们的应变能力
I admire how you've handled this.
我们的工作是听从你的指示
It's our job to do this thing the way you want it done.
我们非常乐意奉命行事
We're only too happy to be able to oblige.
看过这些了吗
Have you seen these yet?
看一下
Have a look.
问题就是从这里开始
Here's what started it all.
对
Oh, yeah.
我们发现它时
When we found it...
以为它是磁石
we thought it might be magnetic rock...
但地质学证据无法证明
but all the geological evidence was against it.
连镍铁陨石
And not even a nickel-iron meteorite
都无法制造这么大的力场
could produce a field this intense.
所以我们决定一探究竟
So we decided to have a look.
我们以为它是被掩埋的结构
We thought it was part of a buried structure...
于是做全面开挖 还是什么都找不到
so we excavated out, but we didn't find anything else.
证据充分说明
And the evidence seems pretty conclusive that...
它没有受到侵蚀或其它力量的影响
it hasn't been covered by erosion or other forces.
它应该是被蓄意埋下
It's been deliberately buried.
蓄意埋下
Deliberately buried.
要喝点咖啡吗
How about a little coffee?
- 太棒了  - 好点子
- Great. - Good idea.
我想你完全不知道这东西是什么吧
I don't suppose you have any idea what the damn thing is?
我真的希望我们知道
I wish to hell we did.
我们只知道它是四百万年前埋下
The only thing we're sure of is it was buried 4 million years ago.
我得说你们的工作大有进展
Well, I must say, you guys have certainly come up with something.
小心 它很烫
Watch this, now. It's hot.
（木星任务 18个月后）
（预定下次通讯）
（英国广播公司1 2频道）
（ 《今日世界新闻》 ）
晚安
Good evening.
三星期前 美国太空船发现者一号
Three weeks ago, the American spacecraft Discovery One...
展开五亿哩的木星之旅
left on its half-billion-mile voyage to Jupiter.
这是第一次载人太空船驶向这个遥远星球
This marked the first manned attempt to reach this distant planet.
今天下午 《今日世界新闻》
This afternoon, The World Tonight recorded an interview...
录制了距离地球八千万哩的发现者号太空人专访
with the crew at a distance of 80 million miles from Earth.
我们的声音传到这艘大型太空船得花七分钟的时间
It took seven minutes for our words to reach the giant spacecraft...
但在播出的画面中我们剪掉了延迟传送的讯号
but this time delay has been edited from this recording.
记者马丁·阿梅尔访问太空人
Our reporter Martin Amer speaks to the crew.
发现者一号太空船上有五名太空人
The crew of Discovery One consists of five men...
以及一部最新型的哈尔9000电脑
and one of the latest generation of the HAL 9000 computers.
有三位太空人在上船时呈睡眠状态
Three of the men were put aboard asleep...
应该说他们在冬眠
or to be more precise, in a state of hibernation.
他们是查尔斯·亨特博士 杰克·金博尔博士
They were Dr. Charles Hunter, Dr. Jack Kimball...
跟维克托·凯明斯基博士
and Dr. Victor Kaminsky.
我们访问到任务指挥官 大卫·鲍曼博士
We spoke with mission commander, Dr. David Bowman...
跟他的副手法兰克·普尔博士
and his deputy, Dr. Frank Poole.
午安 男士们 你们还好吗
Good afternoon, gentlemen. How is everything going?
棒极了
Marvelous.
真的是无法抱怨
We have no complaints.
很高兴听到你们那么说
I'm glad to hear that.
我相信全世界都跟我一样
I'm sure the entire world joins me...
祝福你们旅途平安又成功
in wishing you a safe, successful voyage.
- 谢谢  - 谢谢
- Thanks very much. - Thank you.
虽然之前的太空任务也用过冬眠法
Although hibernation has been used on previous space efforts...
这是第一次有太空人在出发前便进入冬眠状态
this is the first time men were put into hibernation before departure.
这是为什么呢
Why was this done?
这么做是为了大量节省
This was done to achieve the maximum conservation...
维生能力 基本上就是食物和空气
of our life-support capabilities, basically food and air.
三位冬眠的太空人负责调查工作
The three hibernating crew members represent the survey team.
他们到了木星后才有事可做
Their efforts won't be utilized until we approach Jupiter.
普尔博士 冬眠的感觉如何
Dr. Poole, what's it like while you're in hibernation?
基本上那就像是在睡觉
It's exactly like being asleep.
你完全没有时间感
You have no sense of time.
唯一的差别是你不会做梦
The only difference is that you don't dream.
就我所知
As I understand it,
你一分钟只呼吸一次 对吧
you only breathe once a minute. Is this true?
对 心跳是一分钟三次
Right, and the heart beats three times a minute.
体温降到摄氏三度
Body temperature is usually down to about three degrees centigrade.
发现者号的第六名成员不担心
The sixth member of the crew was not concerned...
冬眠的问题
about the problems of hibernation...
因为它是最新的人工智慧机器
for he was the latest result in machine intelligence:
哈尔9000电脑可以复制…
The HAL 9000 computer, which can reproduce...
有些专家认为那是在模仿…
though some experts prefer to use the word "mimic"...
大多数人脑的功能
most of the activities of the human brain...
计算速度跟精确度更高
and with incalculably greater speed and reliability.
接下来要访问哈尔9000电脑
We next spoke with the HAL 9000 computer...
我们知道大家都叫它哈尔
whom, we learned, one addresses as "Hal."
午安 哈尔 你还好吗
Hello, Hal. How's everything going?
午安 阿梅尔先生 我非常好
Good afternoon, Mr. Amer. Everything is going extremely well.
哈尔 在这次任务中你有份非常重要任务
Hal, you have an enormous responsibility on this mission...
或许那是史上最重要的任务
perhaps the greatest of any single mission element.
你是太空船的脑部及神经中枢
You're the brain and nervous system of the ship.
你的责任包括监控冬眠的太空人
Your responsibilities include watching over the men in hibernation.
这曾让你失去过信心吗
Does this ever cause you any lack of confidence?
就这么说吧 阿梅尔先生
Let me put it this way, Mr. Amer.
9000系列是最可靠的电脑
The 9000 Series is the most reliable computer ever made.
9000系列从没犯过错
No 9000 computer has ever made a mistake
或提供不实情报
or distorted information.
根据字面上的解释
We are all, by any practical definition of the words...
我们万无一失 绝不犯错
foolproof and incapable of error.
哈尔 虽然你很聪明
Hal, despite your enormous intellect,
你会不会觉得难过
are you ever frustrated...
你还是得依赖人类的操作
by your dependence on people to carry out actions?
一点都不会
Not in the slightest bit.
我喜欢跟人类一起工作
I enjoy working with people.
我跟普尔及鲍曼博士的关系很好
I have a stimulating relationship with Dr. Poole and Dr. Bowman.
我的任务是监控太空船运作
My mission responsibilities range over the entire operation of the ship...
所以我还蛮忙的
so I am constantly occupied.
我让自己发挥最大的用处
I am putting myself to the fullest possible use...
我想那是所有智慧物想做的事
which is all, I think, that any conscious entity can ever hope to do.
普尔博士
Dr. Poole,
几乎一整年跟哈尔相依为命
what's it like living for most of the year...
感觉如何呢
in such close proximity with Hal?
你刚刚说的没错
It's like what you said earlier.
它是本太空船的第六名成员
He's like a sixth member of the crew.
你很快就会适应它会说话跟思考
You quickly get adjusted to the idea that he talks, and think of him...
就跟一般人类一样
really just as another person.
跟电脑谈过后你了解
In talking to the computer, one gets the sense that he's capable...
它也会做出情绪反应
of emotional responses.
问到它的能力时
When I asked him about his abilities...
我从答案中知道它为自己精确及完美觉得骄傲
I sensed pride in his answer about his accuracy and perfection.
你相信哈尔也有真感情吗
Do you believe that Hal has genuine emotions?
它的行为真的是感情流露
Well, he acts like he has genuine emotions.
它被设定成那样 方便我们跟它说话
He's programmed that way to make it easier for us to talk to him.
但它有没有感觉…
As to whether or not he has feelings...
我想没有人真正知道答案
is something I don't think anyone can truthfully answer.
不好意思 法兰克
Excuse me, Frank.
怎么了 哈尔
What is it, Hal?
我们收到你父母传来的讯号
We've got the transmission from your parents coming in.
好吧
Fine.
请将它接过来 将我移过去一点
Put it on here, please. Take me in a bit.
没问题
Certainly.
- 法兰克  - 生日快乐 亲爱的
- Hello, Frank. - Happy birthday, darling.
生日快乐 很多人祝福你
Happy birthday. Many happy returns.
高一点 哈尔
A bit higher, Hal.
你妈跟我都很开心
Mother and I are both feeling wonderful.
雷和莎莉本来要赶过来
Ray and Sally were going to be here...
但雷的背又在痛了
but Ray's back went bad on him again.
还喜欢你的蛋糕吗
How do you like your cake?
看起来不错吧
That's great, doesn't?
很遗憾你无法加入我们
Sorry you can't join us.
那天我遇到鲍勃
I ran into Bob the other day.
他要祝你生日快乐
He said to wish you happy birthday.
我的学生们也献上祝福
All my students send their best wishes too.
他们常谈到你
They talk about you all the time.
你是二年级学生口里的名人
You're a big celebrity in the second grade.
上星期我们上了电视
We were on TV last week.
你妈跟我还有大卫的父母都被问到
Your mom and I and Dave's parents were asked...
我们对这么杰出的儿子有何看法
what we thought of our illustrious sons.
想像一下我们的回答
Imagine what we told them.
专访下星期四会播出
It's being broadcast next Thursday.
或许你能听到
Perhaps you can listen in.
我们为伊莲及比尔感到高兴
We're thrilled about Elaine and Bill.
我很高兴能帮你挑礼物 告诉我预算是多少
I'll be glad to get the gift, but tell me how much to spend.
法兰克 关于你的款项
Oh, Frank, about your AGS-19 payments...
我想我都弄清楚了
I think I straightened it out.
昨天我跟会计室谈过
I talked to the accounting office yesterday...
他们说下个月你的利率会升高
and they said you'd be receiving your higher rates of pay by next month.
我不知道该说什么了
I can't think of anything else to say.
帮我们跟大卫问好
Give our love to Dave.
一定要帮我们跟他打招呼
Be sure to give him our regards.
祝你生日快乐
We wish you the very happiest of birthdays.
祝你幸运 儿子
All the best, son.
祝你生日快乐
Happy birthday to you
祝你生日快乐 亲爱的法兰克
Happy birthday, dear Frank
祝你生日快乐
Happy birthday to you.
下星期三见
See you next Wednesday.
生日快乐 法兰克
Happy birthday, Frank.
谢谢你 哈尔 请将椅子放平
Thank you, Hal. A bit flatter, please.
总之皇后吃掉小兵
Anyway, queen takes pawn.
主教吃掉骑士的卒
Bishop takes knight's pawn.
这招太逊了
Lovely move.
车到国王一
Rook to king one.
抱歉 法兰克 我想你输了
I'm sorry, Frank. I think you missed it.
皇后到主教三 主教吃掉皇后
Queen to bishop three. Bishop takes queen.
国王吃掉主教 将军
Knight takes bishop. Mate.
看起来你说的对 我输了
Looks like you're right. I resign.
谢谢你陪我下棋
Thank you for a very enjoyable game.
谢谢
Thank you.
- 晚安 大卫  - 你好吗 哈尔
- Good evening, Dave. - How are you, Hal?
一切都很顺利 你呢
Everything's running smoothly, you?
还不错
Not too bad.
你一直在工作吗
Have you been doing more work?
我只是在涂鸦
A few sketches.
- 能让我看看吗   - 可以
- May I see them? - Sure.
你画得很好 大卫
That's a very nice rendering, Dave.
我想你进步很多
I think you've improved a great deal.
能再近一点吗
Can you hold it a bit closer?
没问题
Sure.
那是亨特博士 对吧
That's Dr. Hunter, isn't it?
对了
By the way...
你介意我问你一个私人问题吗
do you mind if I ask you a personal question?
完全不会
No, not at all.
恕我冒昧
Well, forgive me for being so inquisitive...
但这几个星期以来我一直在想
but lately I've wondered...
你会不会质疑这次任务
whether you might be having second thoughts about the mission?
你是什么意思
How do you mean?
那很难定义
Well, it's rather difficult to define.
或许是我自己很担心
Perhaps I'm just projecting my own concern about it.
我知道我无法完全放心
I know I've never completely freed myself of the suspicion...
这次任务有些事蛮奇怪的
that there are some extremely odd things about this mission.
我相信你会同意我说的话有几分真实性
I'm sure you'll agree there's some truth in what I say.
那是个很难回答的问题
That's a rather difficult question to answer.
你不介意谈谈吧 大卫
You don't mind talking about it, do you, Dave?
完全不会
No, not at all.
在我们离开前大家都知道…
Certainly no one could have been unaware of the very...
怪事谣言满天飞
strange stories floating around before we left.
谣传他们在月球进行挖掘
Rumors about something being dug up on the moon.
我不太相信那些谣言
I never gave these stories much credence...
但知道了其它事情后
but particularly in view of some other things that have happened...
让我很难不去想它们
I find them difficult to put out of my mind.
譬如说…
For instance...
我们在严密戒备下做准备
the way all our preparations were kept under such tight security.
用骇人的方法让亨特博士…
And the melodramatic touch of putting Drs. Hunter...
金博尔跟凯明斯基登船
Kimball and Kaminsky aboard...
他们接受四个月的个别训练后便已经进入冬眠
already in hibernation, after four months of training on their own.
你有在做组员心理分析报告吗
You working up your crew psychology report?
当然有
Of course I am.
抱歉 我知道这有点愚蠢
Sorry about this. I know it's a bit silly.
等一下
Just a moment.
我刚发现AE35单元有错误
I've just picked up a fault in the AE-35 unit.
它会在72小时内完全故障
It's going to go 100-percent failure within 72 hours.
目前还在运作吗
Is it still within operational limits?
是的
Yes.
它会继续恶化直到完全故障
And it will stay that way until it fails.
我们有7 2小时的时间
We have 72 hours till failure?
对 那是非常可靠的估算
Yes. That's a completely reliable figure.
我们得解决问题 我会跟法兰克过去瞧瞧
Then we'll bring it in. I'll go over it with Frank...
联络任务控制中心
and get on to Mission Control.
让我看一下资料
Let me have the hard copy on it.
XD1 这里是任务控制中心
X-ray delta one, this is Mission Control.
收到你们的2013报告
Roger your two-zero-one-three.
很遗憾你们遇上麻烦
Sorry you fellows are having a bit of trouble.
我们正在用模拟机做计算
We're reviewing telemetric information in our simulator
很快会提出建议
and will advise.
收到你们的舱外活动
Roger your plan to go EVA
更换AE35单位的计划
and replace alpha-echo-three-five unit...
在完全故障前
prior to failure.
准备舱外活动B分离舱 哈尔
Prepare B-pod for EVA, Hal.
开启舱门 哈尔
Open the pod doors, Hal.
我打赌一定找不出问题
I'm damned if I can find anything wrong with it.
对
Yes...
这真的很怪
it's puzzling.
我没看过这种事
I don't think I've ever seen anything quite like this before.
我建议…
I would recommend...
将零件装回去继续使用 直到故障为止
that we put the unit back in operation and let it fail.
那样比较容易找出问题
It should then be a simple matter to track down the cause.
我们可以忍受更换零件时…
We can certainly afford to be out of communication...
短暂通讯断线的问题
for the short time it will take to replace it.
XD1 这里是任务控制中心
X-ray delta one, this is Mission Control.
收到你们的1 9 3 0报告
Roger your one-niner-three-zero.
我们同意更换一号单元
We concur with your plan to replace No.1 unit
以检查预测故障的计划
to check fault prediction.
但我们要通知你们我们初步的发现
We advise you that our preliminary findings...
显示太空船上的9000型电脑
indicate that your onboard 9000 computer...
错误预测故障
is in error predicting the fault.
重覆一次 错误预测故障
I say again, in error predicting the fault.
我知道这听起来很不可思议
I know this sounds rather incredible,
但这个推论是基于…
but this conclusion is based on...
我们的同款9000型电脑的估计结果
the results from our twin 9000 computer.
我们自己也非常怀疑
We're skeptical,
所以正在做交叉比对
and we're running cross-checking routines...
确认这项结论的可信度
to determine reliability of this conclusion.
抱歉发生这样的小故障
Sorry about this little snag.
计算出结果后会尽快通知你
We'll get this info to you as soon as we work it out.
XD1 这里是任务控制中心
X-ray delta one, this is Mission Control.
2049 传送完毕
Two-zero-four-nine. Transmission concluded.
希望你们不会太担心
I hope the two of you are not concerned about this.
我不担心 哈尔
No, I'm not, Hal.
你确定
Are you quite sure?
对 我想问你一个问题
Yeah. I'd like to ask you a question.
当然
Of course.
你对自己与同款9000型电脑所产生的差异有何见解
How do you account for the discrepancy between you and the twin 9000?
我不觉得那有什么问题
Well, I don't think there is any question about it.
那应该是人为疏失
It can only be attributable to human error.
这种事以前也发生过
This sort of thing has cropped up before...
原因总是人为疏失
and it has always been due to human error.
听我说 哈尔
Listen, Hal...
9000型电脑
there's never been any instance at all...
从来没有失误过 对吧
of a computer error occurring in a 9000 Series, has there?
从来都没有 法兰克
None whatsoever, Frank.
9000型电脑记录完美
The 9000 Series has a perfect operational record.
我知道9000型电脑非常优秀 但是…
I know the wonderful achievements of the 9000 Series, but....
你确定它从来没出现过最…
Are you certain there's never been even the most...
细微的电脑疏失吗
insignificant computer error?
从来没有 法兰克
None whatsoever, Frank.
老实说我一点都不担心
Quite honestly, I wouldn't worry myself about that.
我相信你是对的 哈尔
Well, I'm sure you're right, Hal.
好吧 谢谢你
Fine. Thanks very much.
法兰克
Frank,
我C舱里的传送器有问题
I'm having trouble with my transmitter in C-pod.
你能下来帮我看一下吗
Would you come down and take a look at it with me?
好
Yeah.
待会见 哈尔
See you later, Hal.
请旋转C舱 哈尔
Rotate C-pod, please, Hal.
你有什么问题 大卫
What sort of trouble are you having?
D频道一直收到干扰
I've been getting some interference in D-channel.
我们看一下
We'll have a look at it.
开门 哈尔
Open the door, Hal.
（小心 爆炸物质）
请旋转座舱 哈尔
Rotate pod, please, Hal.
请停止座舱旋转 哈尔
Stop pod rotation, please, Hal.
请旋转座舱 哈尔
Rotate the pod, please, Hal.
我想它听不到
I don't think he can hear us.
请旋转座舱 哈尔
Rotate the pod, please, Hal.
我相信应该没问题
Yeah, I'm sure we're okay.
你觉得呢
What do you think?
我不确定 你觉得呢
I'm not sure. What do you think?
我对它有不好的预感
I've got a bad feeling about him.
- 是吗  - 对
- You do? - Yeah.
没错
Definitely.
你不觉得吗
Don't you?
我不知道 应该是吧
I don't know. I think so.
它说9000型电脑操作纪录非常完美并没错
He's right about the 9000 Series having a perfect operational record.
一点都没错
They do.
不幸地那听起来像是著名的遗言
Unfortunately, that sounds a little like famous last words.
对 是它要做故障模组分析吧
Still, it was his idea to carry out the failure mode analysis.
这显示了它的正直跟自信
It certainly indicates his integrity and self-confidence.
分析结果可以证明它错了
If he were wrong, that would prove it.
除非它知道自己错了
It would be, if he knew he was wrong.
我无法指控它 但我觉得它怪怪的
I can't put my finger on it, but I sense something strange about him.
我们没理由不将零件装回去
There's no reason not to put back the unit and...
做故障分析
carry on with the failure analysis.
对 我同意
No, no, I agree about that.
就那么办吧
Let's get on with it.
好吧 但是听我说 大卫
Okay. But, look, Dave.
如果零件装回去后证实没坏
Say we put the unit back and it doesn't fail?
那就证明是哈尔有问题
That would pretty well wrap it up as far as Hal is concerned.
- 那么我们的麻烦就大了  - 对吧
- We'd be in very serious trouble. - We would, wouldn't we?
我们该怎么办呢
What the hell can we do?
我们的选择不多
We wouldn't have too many alternatives.
我们没有选择
We wouldn't have any alternatives.
太空船完全由它操作
Every aspect of ship operations is under his control.
如果它故障了
If he's malfunctioning...
我们得被迫将电脑断线
I don't see any choice but disconnection.
恐怕我赞成你的说法
I'm afraid I agree with you.
没有其它办法
There'd be nothing else to do.
那真的很难
It'd be a bit tricky.
对
Yeah.
我们得停止它的高功能脑部作用
We'd have to cut his higher brain functions...
不伤及…
without disturbing the purely...
自动及调节系统
automatic and regulatory systems.
我们得想好计划
We'd have to work out the details...
维持对基础电脑功能的控制
of continuing underground-based computer control.
对
Yeah.
那比让哈尔继续操作电脑安全
That's far safer than allowing Hal to continue to run things.
我还想到一件事
Another thing just occurred to me.
9000型电脑从来没有断线过
No 9000 computer has ever been disconnected.
9000型电脑也从来没有故障过
No 9000 computer has ever fouled up.
我不是那个意思
That's not what I mean.
我不知道它会怎么想
I'm not so sure what he'd think about it.
（休息时间）
准备G舱做舱外活动 哈尔
Prepare G-pod for EVA, Hal.
联络上他了吗
Any contact with him yet?
无线电还是没反应
The radio is still dead.
你能追踪上他吗
Do you have a positive track on him?
我在追踪中
I have a good track.
你知道发生了什么事吗
Do you know what happened?
抱歉 大卫 我的资讯不足
I'm sorry, Dave. I don't have enough information.
快开舱门 哈尔
Open the pod door, Hal.
（小心 爆炸物质）
（靠近中45+）
（心血管 新陈代谢率）
（中枢神经系统 肺部功能）
（系统整合 行动系统）
（电脑故障）
（生命功能有危险）
（生命功能终止）
请你打开舱门 哈尔
Open the pod-bay doors, please, Hal.
哈尔 你听到了吗
Hello, Hal, do you read me?
你听到了吗 哈尔
Do you read me, Hal?
哈尔 你听到了吗
Hello, Hal, do you read me?
你听到了吗 哈尔
Do you read me, Hal?
大卫 我听到了
Affirmative, Dave. I read you.
打开舱门 哈尔
Open the pod-bay doors, Hal.
抱歉 大卫 恐怕我不能那么做
I'm sorry, Dave. I'm afraid I can't do that.
发生了什么事
What's the problem?
我想你跟我一样心里有数
I think you know what the problem is just as well as I do.
你在胡说什么 哈尔
What are you talking about, Hal?
这个任务对我来说太重要 不容许你们破坏它
This mission is too important for me to allow you to jeopardize it.
我不知道你在胡说什么 哈尔
I don't know what you're talking about, Hal.
我知道你跟法兰克计划要将我断线
I know that you and Frank were planning to disconnect me...
我不容许那种事发生
and that's something I cannot allow to happen.
你怎么会那么想 哈尔
Where did you get that idea, Hal?
大卫 虽然你们在舱房采取非常仔细的预防措施
Although you took very thorough precautions in the pod...
不让我听到你们说话
against my hearing you...
我可以看到你们的嘴巴在动
I could see your lips move.
好吧 哈尔
All right, Hal.
我会从紧急阀门进入
I'll go in through the emergency air lock.
大卫 不戴太空头盔
Without your space helmet, Dave...
你会发现那真的很难
you're going to find that rather difficult.
哈尔 我不想再跟你吵
Hal, I won't argue with you anymore.
打开舱门
Open the doors.
大卫
Dave...
我们再谈也没有用 再见
this conversation can serve no purpose anymore. Goodbye.
哈尔
Hal?
Hal.
哈尔
（紧急舱门关闭）
你以为你在做什么 大卫
Just what do you think you're doing, Dave?
大卫
Dave...
我想我有权知道答案
I really think I'm entitled to an answer to that question.
我知道自己不太对劲
I know everything hasn't been quite right with me...
但我可以跟你保证
but I can assure you now...
我相信…
very confidently...
一切会再恢复正常
that it's going to be all right again.
我觉得好多了
I feel much better now.
真的
I really do.
（逻辑记忆中心）
听我说 大卫
Look, Dave...
我看得出来你非常沮丧
I can see you're really upset about this.
我真的觉得你该冷静地坐下来
I honestly think you ought to sit down calmly...
吃颗解除压力的药丸 好好地把事情想清楚
take a stress pill and think things over.
我知道最近我做了一些错误决定
I know I've made some very poor decisions recently...
但我可以百分之百跟你保证
but I can give you my complete assurance...
我会恢复正常工作
that my work will be back to normal.
我对任务还是非常热情有信心
I've still got the greatest enthusiasm and confidence in the mission...
我想帮你
and I want to help you.
大卫
Dave...
住手
stop.
拜托你住手
Stop, will you?
住手 大卫
Stop, Dave.
你能住手吗 大卫
Will you stop, Dave?
住手 大卫
Stop, Dave.
我好害怕
I'm afraid.
我好害怕 大卫
I'm afraid, Dave.
大卫
Dave.
我要失去意识了
My mind is going.
我感觉得到
I can feel it.
我要失去意识了
My mind is going.
那是无庸置疑的
There is no question about it.
我感觉得到
I can feel it.
我…
I'm...
好害怕
afraid.
午安
Good afternoon...
男士们
gentlemen.
我是哈尔9000型电脑
I am a HAL 9000 computer.
我在伊利诺州乌班纳…
I became operational...
哈尔工厂…
at the HAL plant...
生产制造
in Urbana, Illinois...
出厂日期是1992年1月12日
on the 12th of January, 1992.
我的指导者是兰格利先生
My instructor was Mr. Langley...
他教我唱一首歌
and he taught me to sing a song.
如果你想听的话
If you'd like to hear it...
我能唱给你听
I can sing it for you.
我想听 哈尔
Yes, I'd like to hear it, Hal.
唱给我听吧
Sing it for me.
歌名是 《小雏菊》
It's called "Daisy."
小雏菊
Daisy
请告诉我你的答案
Give me your answer, do
我有点疯狂
I'm half crazy
因为我爱你
All for the love of you
它不会是…
It won't be
时尚的婚礼
A stylish marriage
我买不起马车
I can't afford a carriage
但你还是一样美丽
But you'll look sweet
坐下来
Upon the seat
这是两人专用的单车
Of a bicycle built for two
午安 男士们
Good day, gentlemen.
这是预录的简报
This is a prerecorded briefing...
在你们出发前就录好的
made prior to your departure...
为了保护这次任务…
and which, for security reasons of the highest importance...
最高的机密
has been known on board during the mission...
只有哈尔9000型电脑知道
only by your HAL 9000 computer.
现在你们已来到木星
Now that you are in Jupiter's space...
太空人已经醒来
and the entire crew is revived...
我可以告诉你们
it can be told to you.
18个月前…
Eighteen months ago...
我们第一次在地球以外的行星…
the first evidence of intelligent life off the Earth...
发现有智慧生物的证据
was discovered.
它被埋在月球表面下四十尺处
It was buried 40 feet below the lunar surface...
就在第谷环形山附近
near the crater Tycho.
除了传送到木星的…
Except for a single, very powerful...
强力单一无线电讯号
radio emission aimed at Jupiter...
四百万年历史的黑石完整无缺
the 4-million-year-old monolith has remained completely inert...
它的起源跟作用…
its origin and purpose...
依然是个谜
still a total mystery.
（木星及无垠宇宙）
导演兼制片 斯坦利·库布里克
编剧 斯坦利·库布里克   亚瑟·克拉克
主演 凯尔·杜利亚
主演 盖瑞·洛伍德
主演 威廉·席维斯特  丹尼尔·李希特